Guide to the Adella Liebenow Wotherspoon Photographs and Papers 1860-2004 PR 400
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Family photographs and documents, 1860-2004
  - Wotherspoon, Adella (Liebenow) (1903-2004)
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Personal copy of Wild Flowers from Whittier (New York: Cupples & Leon Company, 1909), [1912 December 25] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
      Poetry book inscribed "To Adella from the Scolumn [Slocum], December 25, 1912." With a poem by Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon, "The Barefoot Boy," on the front flyleaf.
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Confirmation certificate [in German], 1917 May 20 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
      Ceremony performed by Rev. G. Daeuble, Pastor, St. Peter's German Lutheran Church, Plainfield, New Jersey.
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Gardening certificates, 1980-1996 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
      Five certificates awarded to Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon by the Garden Club of Watchung [New Jersey] (1980), Garden Club of New Jersey (1983, 1991), National Council of State Garden Clubs, Central Atlantic Region (1992), and the Blue Star Memorial Highway Council (1996).
    - Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon. Funeral remembrance cards (2), [2004 January 26] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
      Issued by Higgins Home for Funerals, Watchung, New Jersey.
  - Wulf, Heinrich (circa 1842-1909)
    - Heinrich Wulf. Unidentified document [in German], 1864 August 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
      Issued to Heinrich Wilhelm Friedrich "Wulff."
    - Heinrich Wulf. "Reise Pass" (passport) [in German], 1865 May 26 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
      Issued to Heinrich "Wulff" at Lubeck, Germany.
    - Heinrich Wulf. U.S. Certificate of naturalization, 1872 October 10 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
      Issued by the Court of Common Pleas, New York.
    - Heinrich Wulf. 25th wedding anniversary [in German], 1892 September 13 (Oversize FF, Item 6)
      Certificate commemorating the 25th anniversary of the marriage of "Heinrich Fr. Wilh. Wulf" and "Helene Christiane Brauer" at New York City on September 15, 1867.
  - Wulf, Helene (Brauer) (circa 1840-1897)
    - Helene (Brauer) Wulf. Funeral remembrance card, [1897 June 28] (Offsite-box 4, Volume smaller scrapbook)
      Funeral remembrance card for Helene (Brauer) Wulf. Identified (on scrapbook page) as "Grama Wulf."
  - Wulf, Henry (1876-1912)
    - Henry Wulf. Certificate of sympathy, 1913 March 5 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
      Organization of Gen'l Slocum Survivors, certificate of sympathy issued to Anna C. (Wulf) Liebenow, on the death of her brother, Henry Wulf.
- Series II. ​General Slocum disaster scrapbooks, 1904-1908, 1934
  According to label text from the New-York Historical Society's 2004 exhibition, The General Slocum and Little Germany, both Both Paul and Anna (Wulf) Liebenow kept scrapbooks following the disaster. Edward T. O'Donnell, in his book, Ship Ablaze: The Tragedy of the Steamboat General Slocum (2003), attributes the compilation of both scrapbooks solely to Paul Liebenow. While the exhibition noted different emphases in each volume—sentimental reminders in Anna's, trial coverage in Paul's—there is considerable overlap of material, much of it drawn from the same English- and German-language newspaper coverage of the fire, rescue efforts, memorial ceremonies, and court proceedings. The smaller format volume [in Box 4] includes several photographs: "Our Helen" [identical to the one of Helen Liebenow (1898-1904) in Box 1, Folder 9]; "Grama Liebenow" [Henriette (Pisch) Liebenow (1846-1881)]; "Cousin Frank" [Frank Weber Jr. (1897-1904)]; and a cabinet card portrait of two young girls identified as "Friends lost on Slocum." Also present is a funeral remembrance card for "Grama Wulf" [Anna's mother, Helene (Brauer) Wulf (circa 1840-1897)], and a "hat pin found on North Brother Island, about 2 hours after the burning of the 'Slocum,' the property of one of the victims. Found by Paul Liebenow."
  - Smaller format scrapbook, 1904-1908 (Offsite-box 4)
  - Larger format scrapbook, 1904-1906, 1934 (Offsite-box 5)
- Series III. ​​General Slocum disaster memorial programs, newspaper clippings, ephemera, 1904-2004
  - Journal for the Seventeenth Annual Excursion of St. Marks Evan. Lutheran Church, 323-327 6th Street, New York, Wednesday, June 15, 1904 (photocopy), 1904 June 15 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    Related Materials
    Photocopy of the original journal at The New-York Historical Society under call number Y-q 1904.Jou.
  - Massasoit (ferryboat) crew. Group portrait + copy print (2 folders), [circa 1904?] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19-20)
    Studio cabinet card photograph of the crew of the Massasoit, a Department of Corrections ferryboat. The Massasoit earned four Congressional medals for its rescue and recovery efforts during the General Slocum disaster. Five of the crew are identified: "Todd eng[ineer]," "Jim Duane" [James J. Duane, mate], "Capt. Parkerson" [Fredrick W. Parkinson], "Capt. Wilson," and "Wm. Hatch" [William M. Hatch, chief engineer]. The same image of Hatch appears on a postcard in Box 2, Folder 23, Sleeve 12.
  - Henry Davenport Northrop. New York's Awful Steamboat Horror, [1904] (Offsite-box 3)
    Paul Liebenow's copy of Henry Davenport Northrop's New York's Awful Steamboat Horror (Philadelphia, Pa.: National Pub. Co.?, 1904?), one of several "instant" books of eyewitness accounts published in the wake of the General Slocum disaster. Liebenow or a family member circled the following passage on page 248:
    "Paul Liebenow, with his head swathed in bandages and his hands badly burned, said he had tried in vain to pull down life preservers at the time of the disaster. He knew that others had implored the captain to beach the 'Slocum' at the sunken meadows. He heard of the fire when he was between Ninetieth and Ninety-second streets. Among those killed were two of his children, a sister, a sister-in-law, a niece and a nephew."
    The complete book may be read online, and the New-York Historical Society has an additional copy under call number F128 VK1257.G4 N8.
  - Postcard (1) of "Slocum Monuments", circa 1907 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    Oversize postcard published by the Albertype Co., Brooklyn, N.Y., of the "Slocum Monuments" at Lutheran Cemetery, "Erected on the Plot of the 61 unidentifed dead. In memory of the 1031 who lost their lives on the Steamboat General Slocum in the East River, June 15th, 1904."
  - General Slocum survivors newspaper clippings, 1954, 1957, 2002-2004 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
    Includes obituaries for General Slocum survivors Catherine Connelly (1893-2002), who died at age 109 in 2002, and Adella (Liebenow) Wotherspoon (1903-2004), who was both the youngest survivor and, after the death of Mrs. Connelly, the oldest survivor, when she died at age 100 in 2004. Another obituary details the life of M. Spreen Black, who died in 2002 at the age of 107. Mrs. Black was supposed to attend the St. Mark's Lutheran Church excursion on the General Slocum on June 15, 1904, but her mother asked her not to, thus unwittingly saving her life.
  - Postcards (25) issued by Slocum Memorial Committee of the Queens Historical Society and the Organization of the General Slocum Survivors, 1990-1991, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
    Imagery includes the monument to the unknown dead of the General Slocum disaster at Lutheran Cemetery, Middle Village, Queens, the ship itself, St. Mark's German Evangelical Lutheran Church, funeral processions, memorial services, and William M. Hatch, a crew member of the ferryboat Massasoit, who aided in the rescue.
  - VHS. "Die Slocum brennt! ein Film von Christian Baudissin" ("The Slocum is on Fire! a film by Christian Baudissin"), 1998 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - Certificate of appreciation from the friends of the Slocum Remembrance to Adella Wotherspoon, 1999 June 12 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
  - Paul Segriest, National Park Service. "Interview with Adella Liebenow Wotherspoon", 1999 July 19 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
    Rough draft transcription of an interview conducted for the New-York Historical Society.
  - Postcard (1) of "Niederstein's Restaurant and Catering", [2001] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
    Historical Note
    For 150 years, Niederstein's, at 69-16 Metropolitan Avenue in Middle Village, Queens, served as a gathering place for visitors to nearby Lutheran Cemetery, site since 1905 of the memorial to the unknown dead of the General Slocum disaster. The restaurant closed in February 2005 and was demolished soon after. Card postmarked August 2001.
  - General Slocum disaster annual memorial service programs, 2001-2003 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
    Programs for the 97th (2001), 98th (2002), and 99th (2003) anniversary services at Trinity Lutheran Church, Middle Village, Queens, New York, and for the commemoration in Tompkins Square Park, Manhattan (2003).
  - State of New York. Legislative Resolution, Senate No. 5605, Commemorating the 98th Anniversary of the "General Slocum" steamboat fire, a tragedy which occurred on June 15, 1904, 2002 May 21 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
  - Kenneth G. Leib and Patricia Urevith, "The General Slocum Tragedy: A Historical Partnership", 2003 May 9-10 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
  - Print of General Slocum (Steamboat) on canvas [approximately 4.25 x 5.5 inches], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31)